<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!-- catalog not working ? -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook-Interchange XML V4.2//EN"
	"../docbook/docbookxi.dtd">

<article id='icdb'>

<articleinfo>
	<title><phrase condition="online">[restrict log='none']</phrase>Interchange Guides: Database and Field Descriptions</title>
	<titleabbrev>icdb</titleabbrev>

	<copyright>
		<year>2006</year>
		<holder>Interchange Development Group</holder>
	</copyright>

	<authorgroup>
		<author>
			<firstname>Davor</firstname><surname>Ocelic</surname>
			<email>docelic@icdevgroup.org</email>
		</author>
		<author><firstname>Stefan</firstname><surname>Hornburg</surname>
			<email>racke@icdevgroup.org</email>
		</author>
	</authorgroup>

	<legalnotice>
		<para>
		This documentation is free; you can redistribute it and/or modify
		it under the terms of the &GNU; General Public License as published by
		the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
		(at your option) any later version.
		</para>
		<para>
		It is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
		but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
		MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
		GNU General Public License for more details.
		</para>
	</legalnotice>

	<abstract>
		<para>
		The purpose of this document is to list all pre-defined
		&glos-database;s used by &IC;, describe their purpose and describe
		all their fields.
		</para>
	</abstract>

</articleinfo>


<section id="products">
<title>The "Products" Database</title>
<para>
	The <database>products</database> databases contain items that
	you are offering in your web shop or web catalog.
</para><para>
	The initial database text source file, <filename>products.txt</filename>,
	is usually in an ASCII, &glos-tab-delimited; format.
	Each product listed there should be given a product code, usually
	referred to as &glos-SKU; &mdash; a short code that identifies the
	product on the ordering page and in the &glos-catalog;.
	So the <database>products</database> database must contain
	at least the product SKU (<database class='field'>code</database>),
	<database class='field'>description</database> and 
	<database class='field'>price</database> fileds (or however the
	&conf-PriceField; and &conf-DescriptionField;
	directives have been set). All other information needed in the
	catalog can be placed in additional, arbitrary fields within the same
	table.
</para>
<para>
	The field names must be declared on the first line of the
	<filename>products.txt</filename> file. Accesses from your &IC; pages
	to any other fields within the table will, of course, not execute
	properly.  Field names can
	contain the characters <literal>A-Za-z0-9</literal> and an underscore
	(<literal>_</literal>).
</para>
<para>
	It is important to adjust the &conf-PriceField; and &conf-DescriptionField;
	directives if you change the default field names, or 
	&IC; tags such as &tag-price;, &tag-description;, <tag>item-price</tag> or
	<tag>item-description</tag> will not work.
</para>
<para>
	For each product entry in the text source file, the product code must
	be the first field in the line, and
	must be unique. Product codes can contain the characters
	<literal>A-Za-z0-9</literal>,
	along with hyphens (<literal>-</literal>), underscores
	(<literal>_</literal>), pound signs/hash marks
	(<literal>#</literal>), slashes (<literal>/</literal>) and periods
	(<literal>.</literal>). Note that slashes will
	interfere with &glos-flypage;s; avoid them where ever possible.
</para>
<para>
	The columns in the text source files should be separated by one of the
	approved delimiting
	schemes (TAB, PIPE, or CSV). They are case-sensitive according to the
	underlying database &mdash; be consistent with field names to avoid
	trouble.
	If only the case of the <database>description</database> or
	<database class='field'>price</database> fields have been changed,
	&conf-PriceField; and &conf-DescriptionField; still have to be 
	adjusted appropriately.
</para>
<note>
	<para>
	CSV format is not recommended for the <database>products</database>
	database. It is much slower than TAB- or PIPE-delimited files, and
	dramatically reduces search engine functionality. No field-specific
	searches are possible. Using CSV for any small database that will not
	be searched is fine.
	</para>
</note>
<para>
	More than one database may be used as a products database. If the
	&conf-ProductFiles; directive is set to a space-separated list of
	valid &IC; database identifiers, all listed databases will be
	searched (in the order specified) for any items that are ordered, or
	for product information (such as in
	<code>[price <replaceable>code</replaceable></code> or
	<code>[field <replaceable>code</replaceable>]</code>).
</para>
<para>
	If you are manually modifying databases on-the-fly, it is recommended that
	you lock the files while they are modified. Interchange-supplied import
	routines do this properly on their own.
</para>
</section>





<section id='userdb'>
	<title>User Database</title>
<para>
<phrase condition='online'>[/restrict]</phrase></para>
</section>
</article>
